Guide to the New York Society of the New Church Records 1852-2003 MS 3210
New-York Historical Society
New York Society of the New Church records
1852-2003
New-York Historical Society
New York Society of the New Church
MS 3210
7 Linear feet in 5 record cartons and 1 oversized box.
The New York Society of the New Church Records document the organizational structure and activities of the Swedenborgian congregation primarily located on 35th Street and Lexington Avenue in Manhattan. The documents include minutes, reports, correspondence, and printed matter regarding the functions and administration of the Society. These records reveal the ongoing evolution and struggle of the Society and the 35th Street building to endure economic and societal challenges.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in rough chronological order, with 19th century records preceding 20th century and a few 21st century records. Within each of those broad time periods the material is presented in the finding aid arranged generally by subject. The physical arrangement does not follow that presentation. The disordered 19th and early 20th century documents were unfolded and foldered and the physical sequence follows the sequence of that work. The later 20th century documents remain in their original folders and sequence as delivered to N-YHS.
Biographical / Historical
The New York Society of the New Church was a Swedenborgian denomination, based on the teachings of Emanuel Swedenborg (1688-1772). Swedenborg was a scientist who experienced a spiritual awakening that moved him to develop theological and philosophical texts on the nature of the afterlife, the trinity, and the Second Coming of Christ. Ultimately, his ideas inspired other Christians who sought to reform and reinterpret Christianity, and he is credited with the ensuing theological developments as his texts were revelatory turning points, though Swedenborg himself never attempted to establish a church. Swedenborgism, or the New Church, was founded in 1787, after Swedenborg's death. Swedenborg is said to have influenced other writers, philosophers, and cultural figures such as Robert Frost, Ralph Waldo Emerson, and King Carl XIII of Sweden.
According to the New York Society of the New Church's Historical Sketch (1860; in Box 1, Folder 8), the Society was founded in 1816 by Edward Riley, with the help of James Chesterman and Samuel Woodworth. This group of religious organizers was informally active as early as 1812. Earlier locations of the Society include buildings on Pearl Street and 11th Street, but the archival records were created from and document the Society's primary location on 35th Street. The 35th Street location was deeded to the Society in 1854 and construction of the present-day church building began in 1858. The Society, which also is known as the Society of the New Jerusalem and the New York Association of the New Church, occupied the 35th Street location until it ultimately stopped holding services in 2020 due to declining membership, financial struggles, and the COVID-19 pandemic. The church structure remains, though it is unclear whether, as of 2022, it is currently inhabited or maintained by the Society.
A series of construction and maintenance issues exacerbated the financial decline of the church in the late 20th and early 21st centuries. The Society is described to have been gifted three original lots by James Chesterman in 1854; however, two of these lots were sold by the Board of Trustees when the church was in financial crisis (circa 1990).
The New York Society of the New Church was part of a larger network of regional and national Swedenborgian sects. The archival material reflects ties to New Church societies in Brooklyn, northern New Jersey, and Boston.
Notable clergy who supported the New York New Church include Chauncey Giles (1813-1893), a prolific writer and editor of the New Jerusalem Messenger, also known as the New Church Messenger. For later editions of the New Church Messenger, see Box 3 Folder 12.
The Society was organized by the Board of Trustees and multiple permanent committees and was governed by a constitution and bylaws. The committees included the Church Committee, Ladies Aid Society, Sunday School Committee, Organ Committee, Advertising Committee, and the Flower Committee, amongst other temporary committees. Administrative positions included the Pastor, Treasurer, and Secretary. The overall structure of the Society, and subsequently its documentary record, remains highly consistent from the 19th to 20th century, though this collection does have gaps in that record.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in this collection were donated to the New-York Historical Society by Christopher Bonanos in 2022. Bonanos had retrieved the discarded records from outside the New York Society of the New Church's building on 35th Street and Lexington Avenue in Manhattan. Bonanos described the circumstances on the website Curbed
Scope and Contents
This collection contains printed materials relating to the Society's function and evolution. The records are in two main time periods and distinct formats: 19th century handwritten records that were folded and bundled according to topic (1852-1917) and 20th century records that were typewritten and stored in labeled folders (1954-2003). There are also several oversized ledgers and scrapbooks (1941-1999).
The day-to-day workings of the church administrators are documented in meeting minutes, periodic reports, and financial records such as invoices and receipts. Minutes include those of the Board of Trustees and the various church committees. There are also foundational documents such as the Society's constitution, bylaws, amendments, trustee election certifications, membership rolls, pledge cards, contracts and real estate documents, ledgers, and weekly "Manuals" that served as service materials for in-person worship. Correspondence around key issues such as the valuation and sale of church property, and resignation or appointment of a pastor, or the establishment of a new committee also appear. The collection also includes ephemera such as broadsides, bulletins, and mailers. Clippings, ephemera, and photographs are contained in scrapbooks.
Related Materials
The archives of the General Church of the New Jerusalem and historical papers of New Jerusalem churches in America are held at the Swedenborg Library at Bryn Athyn College: https://brynathyn.edu/swedenborg-library/archives.html. These include the records of various local societies, including a small number of records from New York and Brooklyn found within the General Church of the New Jerusalem record group (RG.004)
Account books.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Church finance -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church records.; Churches -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ledgers (account books); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Midtown Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs; Minutes (administrative records); New Jerusalem Church.; New York (N.Y.) -- Church history.; New York (State) -- Religious life and customs -- 19th century.; Religious facilities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Religious institutions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reports.; Scrapbooks.; Swedenborgians.; General Convention of the New Jerusalem in the United States of America; Giles, Chauncey, 1813-1893; Swedenborg, Emanuel, 1688-1772
- Historical Sketch of the New York New Church Society (monograph), 1860 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Constitution and Bylaws, Amendments of NYSNC and Brooklyn Society, 1865-1879 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Church Committee Reports, 1852-1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
- Church Committee and Finance Records (2 folders), 1875-1879 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 47-48)
- President and Church Committee Report, 1882 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 49)
- Reports of the Book/Library Committee, 1852 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Organ Committee Working Papers, 1870-1894 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  Scope and Contents
  Among other items, this folder includes a church floorplan showing numbered pews.
- Advertising Committee Reports, 1876-1881 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
- Committee on New Pastor, circa 1890s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
- Miscellaneous Committee Reports, 1839-1900 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
- All Committee Reports for Year 1883 (into 1884), 1883-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
- All Committee Reports for Year 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
- All Committee Reports for Years 1885-1886 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
- All Committee Reports, Working Papers for Year 1887, 1881-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
- Ladies Aid Society Annual Reports, 1886-1887, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Reports of the Board of Trustees, 1880-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 45)
- Pastor's Reports, 1875-1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29)
- Secretary's Reports, 1881-1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
- Sunday School Reports and Catalogue, 1852-1882 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Annual Meeting of the NY Society of the New Church. Bulletins, 1881-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- 1907 Annual Meeting Portfolio (Offsite-box 1, Folder 46)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held March 10, 1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held January 1911, 1910 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 40)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held January 1912, 1911 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 41)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held January 1915, 1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 42)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held January 1917, 1916 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 43)
- Annual Reports Submitted at the Annual Meeting Held February 1918, 1917 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 44)
- NYSNC Manual (bound compilation), 1885 November-1889 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Order of Services and Manual, 1883-1896 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- NYSNC Printed Matter and Announcements, 1877-1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Yearbook: New York Society of the New Church, 1892 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Membership Lists, 1886-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Pledge Cards from Church Members, 1897 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Treasurer Reports, 1874-1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
- Financial Reports and Receipts, 1897-1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Receipts and Bills Paid in Year 1869-1870 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
- Expenditures and Contributions, 1875-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous Receipts and Invoices, 1885-1915 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
- Cancelled/Cashed Checks, 1902 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Certificates of Elections of Trustees, 1883, 1888 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Pastor Letters to the Society, 1863-1864 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  Resignation letter of Abiel Silver and acceptance of Pastor position by Chauncey Giles
- Letters and Miscellaneous Papers for Years 1874-1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
- Letters to John B. McGeorge re: donations and membership, 1873-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
- Property Sale Offer, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  Offer to purchase the 35th street property, with related documents.
- Letter to the Board of Trustees from Thomas M. Dillingham Re: Church Property, 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
- Documents to Walter B. Safford Re: Sale of Church Properties and Finances, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Boston Society of the New Jerusalem Manual, 1897 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
- Envelopes and Letterhead, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
- Scrapbook "Volume III", 1930-1932 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook "No. 2", 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook "No. 3", 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
- Minutes: Annual and Quarterly, 1954-1964 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
- Minutes: Annual and Quarterly, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
- Minutes, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
- Minutes: Annual and Quarterly, 1965-1967 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
- Minutes: Annual and Quarterly, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
- Trustee Minutes (2 folders), 1961-1980 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40-41)
- Trustee Minutes, 1971-1986 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 50)
- Trustee Minutes, 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 47)
- Trustee Minutes (3 folders), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 45-46, 49)
- Board of Trustees Correspondence - 1989 to Present, 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 48)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 1993 September-1994 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 44)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 1994 September-1995 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 43)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 1997 July 1-1998 June 30 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 1999 July 1-2000 June 30 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 2001 July 1-2002 June 30 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- NYSNC Board of Directors Minutes, 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
- Church Committee Minutes Extra Copies, 1967 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
- Church Committee Minutes, 1969 September-1971 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
- Church Committee Minutes Before 1975, 1967-1975 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
- Church Committee Minutes, 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
- Church Committee Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
- Church Committee Minutes, 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
- Church Committee Minutes, 1992 September-1993 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
- General Ledger, 1941-1953 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
- General Ledger, 1983-1988 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
- General Ledger, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
- General Ledger, 1991 July 1-1992 June 30 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
- General Ledger, 1998 July 1-1999 June 30 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
- Account Book for Members' Weekly Offerings, 1956-1966 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
- Account Book for Members' Weekly Offerings, 1966-1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Budgets (One Copy), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
- Ladies Aid By-laws and Constitution, 1955-1971 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
- Ladies Aid Treasurer's Report, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
- Ladies Aid: Paid Bills, 1977-1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
- Ladies Aid Treasurer Reports, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 51)
- Pastor's Emergency Fund - Inactive Since 1976, 1964-1975 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
- Church Bulletins, 1954-1955 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
- Church Bulletins (2 folders), 1956-1958 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Church Bulletins, 1984 September-1985 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
- Church Bulletins, 1985 September-1986 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
- New York Association of the New Church Bylaws, 1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
- NYSNC Bylaws, 1957 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
- Research Committee Letters, Program, and Suggestions, 1957-1959 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
- Research Committee Program, 1958 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
- Project Link, 1955-1974 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
- Prayer Fellowship (Material Mimeo'd For Mrs. D. Mack), 1958 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
- Group Dynamics Course, 1961 February (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
- Questing Committee Report, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
- Out of Touch Project, 1963 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
- New Church Messenger, 1963-1971 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
- Organ Committee (Ad Hoc), 1965-1966 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
- Summer Program - Children - East Midtown, 1965 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
- Houseparty, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 52)
- Pamphlet - For Those In Sorrow, 1969 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
- Church Women United, 1969-1974 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24)
- Concert Series (3 folders), 1970-1974 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 25-27)
- Advertising, 1970-1979 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 42)
- Book Inventory, 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
- General Information for Clergy, 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
- Swedenborgian Publishing Association (Defunct as of 1985), 1954-1983 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
- General Convention of the New Jerusalem of the USA, 1954-1970 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
- General Church - N.Y. Circle, 1960-1967 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 29)
- N.Y. 1971 Committee For Convention, 1960-1966 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
- President's Address British Congregation, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
- Constitutions (other than New York), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 28)
- Church of the Neighbor (Brooklyn) Photographs, circa 1950s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
- Church of the Neighbor Photograph Box, circa 1950s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
  This box held the photographs now in folder 18
- Suffolk County Council of Churches, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
- The New World Order; an interpretation of the world situation--social, political, economic, religious, by Charles Thomas Carpenter (Monograph), 1944 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
- Empty Labeled Folders, undated, 1990-1999 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
- Fragments, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)